Inventory of the William Meade Papers 1807-1861
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
William Meade Papers, 1807-1861.
Special Collections, College of William and Mary
Mss. 74 M46
117 items.
Personal and business correspondence, 1807-1861, of the Right Reverend William Meade, minister of the Protestant Episcopal church, who was elected the third bishop of Virginia in 1841.
William Meade
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
Purchased: 116 items, July 1974.
Backlog: 1 item.
Biographical/Historical Information
William Meade (1789-1862) was born on 11 November 1789 in Frederick County, Virginia, the son of Colonel Richard Kidder Meade, an aide on General George Washington's staff during the Revolution, and Mary Fitzhugh Grymes. He attended a private school, Carter Hall, in Virginia and then entered the junior class at the College of New Jersey [Princeton University] in 1806. He graduated in 1808 and was valedictorian of his class.
Meade studied for the ministry of the Episcopal church under the Reverend Walter Dulaney Addison, the evangelical rector of St. John Parish, Maryland. Before his ordination, Meade married Mary Barnwell in 1810. They had three sons before her death in 1817. In 1820, he married Thomasia Nelson; they had no children.
Meade was ordained deacon in the Protestant Episcopal Church by Bishop James Madison of Virginia on 24 February 1811. He was ordained priest in the Protestant Episcopal Church by Bishop Claggett of Maryland several years later on 29 January 1818. In 1814, he became the minister for Frederick County, and in 1821 he became the rector of Christ Church, Winchester. With the help of Bishop Moore and William Holland Wilmer, they founded the Protestant Episcopal Seminary in Virginia in Alexandria in 1823. Meade was an opponent of slavery and was one of the charter members who met in Washington, D.C., in December 1816 to organize the American Society for the Colonizing the Free People of Color in the United States.
On 29 May 1829 Meade was elected assistant bishop of Virginia on the first ballot and was consecrated on 19 August 1829. He served in this capacity until 12 November 1841, when Bishop Moore died and he became the third bishop of Virginia. He served in that position until his death.
Meade was strongly opposed to secession, but when Virginia left the Union he supported it. After the North-South split of the church, the first preliminary meeting of the dioceses in the Confederate States met in Montgomery, Alabama, 3-6 July 1861, and the second meeting was in Columbia, South Carolina, 16-24 October 1861. As senior bishop, Meade presided over the Convention in South Carolina where they drew up the constitution of the Protestant Episcopal Church in the Confederate States.
Meade died on 14 March 1862, in Virginia.
Scope and Content Information
Correspondence, 1807-1861, of the Right Reverend William Meade who was a minister of the Protestant Episcopal Church and third Bishop of the Church in Virginia. The early correspondence pertains to his studies at Princeton and his decision to enter the ministry. Subsequent correspondence deals with religious controversy, particularly after his election as Assistant Bishop of Virginia in 1829. The discipline of clergy and laity and disagreement over doctrinal issues form an important part of the collection as well as his referral to his concern for the religious instruction of slaves. Among his correspondents were Richard Channing Moore, William Rollinson Whittingham and J. H. Wingfield.
An additional letter separated yet belonging to the collection can be found under collection number: Sm. Coll. Add. 20.
Arrangement
Organization
This collection is arranged into 9 Series: 1. Correspondence, 1800-1810, 2. Correspondence, 1811-1820, 3. Correspondence, 1821-1830, 4. Correspondence, 1831-1840, 5. Correspondence, 1841-1850, 6. Correspondence, 1851-1860, 7. Correspondence, 1861-1870, 8. Correspondence, Undated, 9. Correspondence - Addition.
Arrangement
This collection of correspondence is arranged chronologically by date with those items without dates found at the end.
Index Terms
Persons:
Wingfield, J. H.; Moore, Richard Channing, 1762-1841.; Whittingham, William Rollinson, 1809-1879.
Corporate Names:
Episcopal Church--Virginia.
Occupations:
Episcopal Church--Virginia--Clergy.
Components List
  Series 1: Correspondence, 1800-1810
- Correspondence, 1800-1810., 7 items. (Box-folder 1:1)
  - John Weylie, Manchester [?], to William Meade, Princeton, New Jersey, 9 June 1807., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Refers to the "late rumpus" at Princeton [for which Meade was expelled but later readmitted]; Weylie declares that he would have acted in the Princeton affair as did Meade; warns Meade not to fall in love as has Weylie; mentions mutual acquaintances, health, and other personal affairs.
  - John Weylie, Manchester [?], to William Meade, Princeton, New Jersey, 30 July 1807., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Commends Meade for excellent letter writing ability; confides that Meade's "account of the behaviour of Dr. Smith on the memorable to [the] [4]th of July is truly shocking." [Smith apparently forbade the Princetonians from drinking on that day]; advises Meade, in answer to Meade's question, on a "proper course of reading' discusses academic matters; approves Meade's plan for "kissing the girls"; reports health matters; discusses other personal matters.
  - M. L. Custis, Alexandria, Virginia to William Meade, Princeton, New Jersey, December 1807., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Explains that the duties of a daughter, mother, and mistress so occupied her time that she could not correspond as she wished; asks Meade to give her regards to her brother; asks Meade to procure book for her; discusses personal matters.
    Including TCy of ALS. 4 pages.
  - John Weylie, Carter Hall [Clarke County, Virginia, home of Burwell family], to William Meade, Princeton, New Jersey, 28 Dec[embe]r 1807., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Weylie reminisces on the days of his tutelage of Meade at Carter's Hall; discusses the health of mutual acquaintances, and other personal matters concerning them; reports that he has twenty-two pupils, ranging from six to twenty, all of whom Weylie claims are "very clever fellows;" discusses romantic affairs throughout the letter.
  - John Weylie, Annfield [Virginia], to William Meade, Princeton, New Jersey, 10 April 1808., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Comments on the art of writing with ease; argues that it is an art mastered only by much labor, and that success in writing is measured by one's ability to conceal the labor involved; reports that Weylie thought Meade was going to study law and that Meade's decision to study Divinity will not bring him worldly wealth, but will afford him great honour as an "Ambassadour from Heaven;" states reasons why Weylie considers himself unfit for the ministry. Weylie congratulates Meade on his decision and expresses approval that Meade will be successful in his calling.
    Including TCy of ALS. 7 pages.
  - John Weylie, Audley [Virginia], to William Meade, Princeton, New Jersey, 7 Sep[tembe]r 1808., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Weylie laments his misfortune in having recently been spurned in romantic overtures made to a mutual acquaintance; he is depressed and is avoiding the company of others as the visiting season has started.
    Including TCy of ALS. 3 pages.
  - M. L. Custis, Arlington, [Virginia], to William Meade, Fredeick, [Virginia], 30 January 1810., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Congratulates Meade on his impending marriage to Mary Nelson; expresses hope of a summer visit from Meade; expresses desire that the gospel should change hearts, and mourns over her "most depraved family of slaves;" discusses mutual acquaintances and asks Meade to greet certain friends and relatives.
  Series 2: Correspondence, 1811-1820
- Correspondence, 1811-1820., 5 items. (Box-folder 1:1-2)
  - W[illiam] Meade, and M[ary] N]elson] M]eade], n.p. to "sister" Susan Meade, Arlington, [Virginia], 1 Feb[ruary] 1811., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Mary Meade acknowledges the congratulations of her sister-in-law on the birth of her recently-born son Philip; gives a description of the baby; in the closing part of the letter, William expresses his love for the baby and sends his greetings.
  - Richard Channing Moore, New York, [N.Y.], to Edmund J. Lee, n.p., 17 Feb[ruar]y 1814., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Informs Lee that Moore will accept the episcopal office [Bishop of Virginia]; having thoroughly considered the offer of the Virginians, Moore declares that he will be zealous in the service of his office.
    Including TCy of ALS. 2 pages.
  - W[illia]m Meade, Winchester, Virginia, to Mr. Edmond Lee, Alexandria, District of Columbia, [Virginia], [July 15]., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Expresses sorrow that he didn't see Lee when Lee passed through his neighborhood; discusses private correspondence and other personal matters.
  - [Bishop] Richard Channing Moore, Richmond [Virginia], to Rev. W[illia]m Meade, n.p., 26 March 1816., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    The bishop writes concerning the settlement of a Mr. Orrell at Martinsburgh; Moore relates that his vestry has warned him about resigning his present charge before a fund was provided for the Episcopate's support; the church has received an assistant, pending "secure and permanent support" for a clergyman; Moore thanks Meade for his support; Moore expresses joy upon learning of Meade's success in Winchester and wishes him continued blessings.
  - [Bishop] Richard Channing Moore, Richmond, [Virginia], to Rev. W[illia]m Meade, n.p., 12 Feb[ruar]y 1817., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Regrets the transfer out of the diocese of Mr. Hawley of Culpeper and Orange; expresses some hesitancy about Meade's itineranting, but commends him to the "throne of grace for counsel;" relates his pleasure in Meade's promise to preach the prayer book and tract sermon; Moore reports that the state of religion in his own parish is not as lively as he would like; expresses desire to be in close contact with Meade because he wishes to frequently consult him. [The tone of this letter is one of great respect for Meade].
  Series 3: Correspondence, 1821-1830
- Correspondence, 1821-1830., 6 items. (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Francis B. Whiting, Fauntly, [Virginia ?], to Rev. William Meade, "Mountain View," [Millwood, Virginia], 8 April 1822., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    James Hay, W[illia]m Hay, and Francis B. Whiting all attest that Dr. [Dudley] Burwell was intoxicated at Carter's Hall ca. Dec., 1821 on a Saturday night; he reportedly took communion on Sunday and played cards for money.
  - [Rev.] G. W. Ridgeley, Philadelphia [Pennsylvania], to Rev. W[illia]m Meade, Millwood, Virginia, 18 Dec[ember] 1826., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Written on a printed circular which relates Meade's refusal of the office of Asst. Bishop of Pennsylvania, probably because of the opposition of the Bishop; the circular asks that while the present Bishop lives that no Asst. Bishop be named; Meade is recommended as the candidate for the joy when it opens; it is signed by Geo[rge] Boyd, G. T. Bedell, and Samuel Robbins; Ridgeley asks Meade to clarify his position for him.
  - W. R. Whittingham, New york, [New York], to Reverend William Meade, Millwood, Virginia, 31 August 1827., 7 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Assures Meade that his objection to the Baltimore edition of Mrs. Sherwood's stories is founded on a misconception; gives passages from Sherwood and Bishop Kemp showing that both are in accord with episcopal teaching; Whittingham also defends the use of Bp. Hobart's catechism; he noted that the Sherwood stories and the Hobart catechism were both recommended, and not contained in "any part of the [Church's] system of instruction."
    Including TCy of ALS. 8 pages.
  - Phillip Meade, Carlisle [Pennsylvania ?] to William Meade, "Mountain View," [Millwood], Virginia, 24 January 1828., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Explains to his father the "rebellion" among the students against faculty; assures his father that he has had no part in the rebellion; discusses personal matters.
    Including TCy of ALS. 5 pages.
  - W. R. Whittingham, New York, [New York], to Rev. William Meade, Millwood, Virginia, 2 April 1828., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Whittingham, of the Sunday School Union, assures Meade that he will "hear no more of Sherwood's stories or [Bishop Hobart's] [of N.Y., an avowed High Churchman] catechism; asks Meade's opinion on other works.
  - [William Meade], n.p. to Rev. [Adam Empie, Pres. of the College of William and Mary, Williamsburg, Virginia], 20 April [sic] 1829., 4 pages. ALS. Possibly Draft. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Responds to letter which Empie wrote questioning whether he can support Meade for Asst. Bishop and questioning his Churchmanship; argues that he does not think Empie's views "untenable" because some "learned and pious men have held different views;" charges Empie is wrong in seeking to set up his own standards [for admission to the ministry]; argues that the Church has never insisted that Ministers from other churches entering into the episcopal ministry renounce their former ordination; assures Empie of Meade's respect for Empie's having acted "under a sense of duty."
  Series 4: Correspondence, 1831-1840
- Correspondence, 1831-1840., 12 items. (Box-folder 1:3)
  - William Meade, Millwood Fred. 85 [?], [Virginia] to anonymous Bishop, 30 May 1832., 5 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Replies to Bishop's questions about a revival in Fredericksburg; assures him that they are conducted in a godly manner; notes that the annual convention of Virginia was also marked by revival spirit.
  - W[illiam] Meade, Millwood, [Virginia], to Rev. George W. Nelson, Richmond, [Virginia], 4 March 1843., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Asks him to send annual sum in support of ministry [?]; complains of ministers leaving their parishes for other ones and the difficulty of filling their places; discusses health and other personal matters.
  - The Will of James Ship given to William Meade, 23 April 1834., 3 pages. ADS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Orders just debts paid; daughters Charlotte F. and Ann T. Ship to have an annuity of $300 each until twenty-five; Susan A. Ship to have annuity of $100 for life; Penelope Stribling, $50 a year for life; Hector Bell received horse; gives to Charlotte F. [slaves], Judy and two children, Harry and Lucy, Sarah and Jerry; gives to Ann t., Jim and wife, and two children, annuities to be raised from land rent; estate shall be divided evenly among children at age 25; Bishop Meade and his brother David to direct the education of any grandchildren if Ship's daughters die; Hector Bell and Uncle John Ship appointed executors; David Meade made guardian of the children.
  - Memo of William Meade, 23 April 1834., 2 pages. ADS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Meade recounts his receiving of James Ship's will and certified Ship's coherent state.
    Including TCy of ADS. 4 pages.
  - W[illiam] Meade, Coalsmouth, Kanhawa [sic] [Co., Virginia], [West Virginia], to "sister," Mary Meade, Millwood, Virginia, 3 June, 1834., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Expresses concern for his children; gives his travel itinerary for the month--traveling and preaching widely throughout Virginia; gives instructions regarding family and home.
  - W[illia]m Meade, "Mountain View," [Millwood], [Virginia], to Mrs. Judith Nelson, Hanover City [?], 28 July 1834., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Assures Mrs. Nelson that he will give her son Robert [who has apparently lived with Meade] a good recommendation for Bristol College; excuses Nelson of debt owed.
    Including TCy of ALS. 1 page.
  - W[illiam] Meade, Norfolk [Virginia], to Mrs. Thomasia Meade [wife], Alexandria, District of Columbia [Virginia], 18 Jan[uary] [1835]., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Having arrived in Norfolk and preached there, Meade reflects on Frederick [the parish which he just left]; asks God for grace to fulfill charge and tells wife he awaits her coming; discusses matters of family, weather, and health.
  - William Meade, n.p. to Dr. Shelth, n.p., 20 March 1835., 5 pages. Folio. Cy of LS (signature not Meade's). (Box-folder 1:3)
    Explains that Bishop Moore complained to him about certain meetings in the seminary [at Alexandria] among students in which they exceeded the bounds of exhorting and were preaching; reports that he encouraged the seminary students not to engage in such and expresses sorrow that [Sheith] had thought he had censured the meetings altogether, for which he [Sheith] took Meade to task.
  - W[illia]m M[eade], Norfolk, [Virginia], to Rev. Nicholas Cobbs, Lynchburg, Virginia, 9 November 1835., 2 pages. LS.[signed, but not in Meade's hand]. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Invitation to Cobbs to be assistant to Meade during the six months of the year that Meade resides in Norfolk; tells him that the large congregation would welcome him and the "the materials for Ministerial operation [are] very good."
    Including TCy. 2 pages.
  - William Meade, Norfolk, [Virginia], to W[illiam] P. C. Johnson, n.p., 5 March 1836., 2 pages. LS.[not in Meade's hand]. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Gives Johnson who had been suspended from his parish, advice to depart for Clarksburg or Parkersburg, where he may secure a ministerial position; Meade also gives a testimonial for Johnson which Johnson can use as a letter of introduction in the western Virginia parishes.
  - W[illiam] Meade, Norfolk [Virginia], to Rev. Cyrus Jacobs, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 26 April 1836., 5 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Lists a series of objections which Meade feels prevents him from heading the subscription for Bristol College; argues that Alexandria Seminary needs support first, that Virginia money should be put to use in Virginia first; expresses resentment over a thinly-veiled threat if the Virginians fail to cooperate.
  - Wk[illiam] Meade [Asst. Bishop of Virginia], n.p. to the Vestry of Bruton Parish, [Williamsburg, Virginia], 28 June 1836., 5 pages. AL. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Meade, having read in a Richmond paper of the vestrymen's dissatisfaction with an act passed at the recent Church Convention in Fredericksburg, warns them not to "excite opposition throughout the Parishes; [apparently the Convention voted no to allow non-communicants to be seated in the ecclesiastical assemblies]; notes that the attempt of the vestry to [state-wide] "allay the laity and clergy against each other; "warns them not to bring disfavor upon the College [of Wm. and Mary] by having "no Episcopal services in the place [Williamsburg] notes that non-communicants are afforded more rights than in other churches; argues that it was necessary to restrict [the assemblies] because "any" of the non-communicants practiced "gambling, horseracing, and drinking" during the convention; refers to them as "notorious gamblers, infamous adulterers, and prophane [sic] swearers; "informs them that the Church will not change its mind and "would sooner see a number of her parishes severed from her," than revoke an act of conscience; urges them to alter their course and sue for peace.
    Including TCy of AL. 7 pages.
  Series 5: Correspondence, 1841-1850
- Correspondence, 1841-1850., 43 items. (Box 1-2)
  - W[illiam] Meade, Richmond, [Virginia], to Rt. Rev. [W.] R. Whittingham, Baltimore, [Maryland], 14 Octo[ber] 1840., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Congratulates Whittingham on his consecration as Bishop of Maryland; expresses hope that as Bishop, Whittingham will share Meade's concern for the religious instruction of the slaves; declares that the "Oxford writers" have "fallen into many mischievous errors."
  - W[illiam] Meade, Report of Agreement with Mr. Lippett, 22 May 1841., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Meade informed Lippett that the Trustees could not "ensure" him for "1000th," which he required in the occupying of the station vacated by a Mr. Meade [Editor of the Southern Churchman]; Lippett refused Meade's personal guarantee of "1000th"; offers to loan Lippett "200th"; complains that most ministers simply accept their position with some uncertainty as to salary and that a like dependence on Providence should be sufficient for Lippett to take the Editor's post [of the Southern Churchman].
  - William Meade, Millwood, Virginia to the minister and church warden of Tillotson Parish, Buckingham County, Virginia, 12 Jan[uary] 1842., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Asks the wardens to hold an inquiry into the case of one of their expelled members [J. M. Fackler] who had applied to Meade, asking for an inquiry, Meade cites the applicable church rules and asks the board of inquiry to report their findings to him so that he may make a judgment.
  - William Meade, Millwood, [Virginia], to J. M. Fackler, n.p., 12 Janu[ary] 1842., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Informs Fackler that he has instructed the church to investigate Fackler's case and report the findings to Meade; encourages Fackler to abstain from communion during the course of the investigation.
  - W[illiam] Meade, Millwood, [Virginia], to Rev. J. H. Morrison, Buckingham, Virginia, 15 Janu[ary] 1842., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Tells Morrison of his correspondence with Fackler and urges Morrison to conclude the matter [of Fackler's exclusion from communion].
  - W[illiam] Meade, Norfolk, [Virginia], to Mary [Meade], n.p., 4 July 1842., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Reports travel itinerary; states that health is as usual; Meade preaches but seldom, confining himself mostly to the duties of the Bishopric.
  - W[illiam] M[eade], n.p., to [Rev. Paul] Trapin, n.p., 27 Decem[ber] 1842., 1 pages. Extract of AL. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Asserts that as Bishop he is "frequently led" to leave the decision of whether a minister should receive an appointment to the consent of the minister and the congregation; expresses approval of Mr. Smith's [?] ministry.
  - W[illiam] Meade, Millwood, [Virginia], to the Editor of the Banner, n.p., 26 January 1843., 7 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Asks that the Banner editor publish a statement by Meade made in response to the Banner's account of a former Methodist-turned-Episcopal Priest returning to the Methodist Church; notes that the former Methodist was apparently sincere when ordained and examined by Meade and that this desertion was a singular case; argued that nothing more that adherence to the prayer book and the articles of the church, if a minister is sound in the gospel, should be required for entrance into the episcopal ministry; believed that if clergy and laity must renounce any previous non-episcopal church connections as false that this will turn away prospective clergy and laity.
    Including TCy of ALS. 6 pages.
  - W[illiam] Meade, Alexandria, [Virginia], to Rev. E. R. Lippett, Alexandria, [Virginia] D--of --Co., 10 May 1843., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Informs Lippett that his account has been examined and that the subject over which Meade and Lee have disagreement "should be freely considered in the presence of suitable persons;" aks him to bring two witnesses to Lee's house for discussion.
  - W[illiam] Meade, "Mountain View," [Millwood, Virginia], to Cassius Lee, Alexandria, Virginia, 31 Janu[ary] [18]44., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Comforts his friend on the loss of Lee's wife; quotes scripture and poetry to console him.
  - W[illiam] Meade, Mecklenburg, [Virginia], to Mary Meade, Millwood, Virginia, 17 June [18]44., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)